And in the previous video of producer
transaction part, we have already seen
how
transaction is handled at producer side.
Now, how transaction or the records
which are part of the transaction
are handled by consumer that we will see
today.
So,
the records
can be only in three state. One is open,
like ongoing.
One is committed
and aborted. So, records can be a part
of transaction which is aborted or
committed or this transaction is still
open.
So, how do you know a transaction is
still open? Generally, let's say this is
a record.
Okay. So, this is a part of this
producer ID and epoch. So, this is
producer ID and epoch.
And this is is transaction true. Okay.
So, this is part of a transaction, this
transaction.
But there is no control record. So,
means this is still open. No no yet
control record for commit or abort it.
For committed, you will have a record
and then for this record, producer ID
and epoch, you have a control record.
Commit.
Similarly, for abort, similarly, you
have producer ID epoch.
PID and epoch.
This is is transaction true, control
false. So, this is a record. And for
this record, there is a control record
true.
Same producer ID epoch, but with abort.
Okay. So, this is the only three
possible state. And also in the
producer, I told you that
transaction
in producer is single-threaded.
Okay. Single-threaded means, let's say
transaction one.
When the transaction one is open, you
cannot have another transaction open.
Okay. So, at a time, you can have one
transaction.
So, this producer ID and epoch is
sufficient to uniquely identify the
transaction.
Okay. So, let's say this is
For example, you are starting a new
transaction, begin transaction.
So, you have PID
one.
Epoch, let's say zero.
One, epoch is zero. You have its record.
And then you have a control record.
Okay. After this control record only,
whether commit or abort, you can another
have another transaction.
Okay. The same PID, same producer ID,
same epoch.
Okay. And its record. So, after that,
you can still have same producer ID
zero.
Epoch is still zero. Its record.
And then its control record, whether
commit or abort.
So,
it is easily understandable that once
you have a record,
you can have so many
send events. You can have so many
events. Let's say send.
Send.
Order events again.
Partition P2. Let's say this is
partition P2 of order hyphen events
only.
You can send multiple send records.
Order hyphen events, partition P2. You
can have multiple events.
Okay. Possible. Okay.
But
till the one transaction,
after that, you will do commit or abort,
right?
So, after this control record only,
you can have another
is transaction equals to true.
Okay. With the same producer ID epoch
and then its control.
Okay. So, things will get more clear,
but at this point of time, all I want is
that
our record can be in three state,
ongoing, commit, abort.
And this producer ID and epoch is
sufficient to uniquely identify the
transaction.
And
as we proceed further, things will get
more clear.
Now, the question might comes that,
okay,
how consumer
knows that what to do with open
transaction,
committed transaction,
or aborted transaction? What to do?
So, there is a one important concept,
LSO, last stable offset comes into the
picture.
So, last stable offset, you can consider
it as a pointer.
This LSO points to the first message
that is open.
Okay.
Or you can say that first message that
belongs to an open transaction.
For example,
you have begin transaction.
Send event, send event, send event, send
event. You have multiple, but currently
commit or aborted not yet happen.
So, you have And all goes to the same
topic and same partition. For example,
so you have multiple
offset zero,
offset one, offset two.
Okay. So, this record goes at offset
zero. This got offset one, offset two.
But
commit and abort not yet happen.
Okay.
So,
LSO points to the first message that
belongs to open transaction.
So, LSO points to offset zero.
So, means this is still open.
Okay. First message of the open
transaction.
Understand with this an example.
Everything get clear.
Let's say
this is a topic order hyphen event,
partition P2 and its log file.
In this all log file, I have five
offset. The first offset,
zero.
PID five, epoch zero, is transaction
true, record one. So, consider that it
is a transaction one. So, you have one
producer.
Okay. Let's say producer one.
So, it
transaction is going on.
Its transaction is going on. It has PID
five.
Epoch is zero. Okay. And it has put one
record, send.
So, this is its record.
Then I have another offset, another
record, PID five, epoch zero. So, again,
the same part of a same transaction. PID
five, epoch zero.
And another send it might have done. So,
which goes to
offset one.
Currently, it is open. No commit, no
offset yet done.
Now,
offset two, PID eight. Some different
producer ID, epoch one. So, some
different producer. Let's say producer
two.
And its transaction, begin transaction.
It has PID
eight. Epoch one.
Okay. And is transaction true, just
begin transaction. So, record one. So,
it has make one send.
So, this is its record.
Similarly, I have PID five, epoch zero.
PID five, epoch zero. So, this is the
one, this transaction. We are talking
about this transaction. I already told
you in
transaction in a particular producer,
it's single-threaded. So, till this
transaction is not yet committed or
aborted, no other transaction can start.
Okay.
So, now, PID five, epoch zero. So, means
I am talking about this transaction.
Its control equals to true. So, this is
a control record. And it is committed.
So, means it is doing commit here.
Okay. And it is committed.
So, means this record transaction one,
this two.
PID five, epoch zero.
This is committed here.
Okay. It has a control record.
Now, at offset four, PID nine, epoch
zero. So, here we are talking about,
let's say producer three.
It has a begin transaction.
PID nine.
Epoch
zero.
It made its first send.
Record comes.
After that, offset five, PID nine, epoch
zero. So, this transaction, this
transaction we are talking about, it has
a control record true, commit. So, it
made a commit.
So, this is also committed.
But here, if you see,
this transaction, this transaction is
still open. It is not yet committed or
aborted.
This is still open.
So, what how
how consumer read this
events?
Okay. So, for first thing first, I told
you that LSO plays a major role. LSO is
that
first message that belongs to open
transaction.
So, it goes from the sequential offset
zero one. What is the first
you can say that record which is open?
Offset two.
This is open. It is not yet closed.
Transaction two.
Uh PID eight, epoch one. It is not yet
open. Okay.
So, LSO
equals to two.
So, it's a pointer.
After that, no matter you have offset
six, offset 10, these are also open,
doesn't matter. LSO only points to the
first record which is open.
Okay.
Now,
how consumer get benefited with this LSO
information?
So, consumer, remember that
whenever
the consumer read from broker, broker
always delivered the data in order
from the partition. So, in this
partition two,
so whatever the consumer will read, it
will read in order.
Offset zero, then one, then two, then
three, whatever. Okay? So, it should be
ordering.
So, how consumer
benefited with this LSO information?
So, consumer first we have to add a
spring.kafka.consumer.properties.isolation.level.
So, read uncommitted is the default.
Even if you don't write it, the default
is read uncommitted.
Uncommitted means that read everything.
And remember that the broker never
return control records. Is control
equals to true? Broker never return it.
So, it is filtered
at broker layer itself.
Filtered at broker layer itself.
So,
when you have isolation level read
uncommitted, which is default,
even if you don't write it, it is
uncommitted only,
you will get all the records.
You will get offset zero,
offset one,
offset two, this is a control record, so
this will get a skip,
offset four,
this is offset five is control record,
so this will be skipped. So, you will
get zero, one, two, and four.
You will get zero, one, two, and four.
Only skip is control record, which is
filtered by broker itself.
So, no matter
whether it's a transaction record part
of a transaction which is committed or
aborted or open, doesn't matter. When
you have read uncommitted, you are able
to see everything.
But,
when you choose isolation level read
committed,
means
what all
records would be visible to you? You
will all the records which are marked as
committed would be visible.
Non-transactional would be visible. The
records which are not part of any
transaction, that would be visible.
But, aborted records, the records which
are part of aborted transaction, that
won't be visible.
And also,
the open transactions,
which are not either committed or
aborted, that won't be visible, too.
Okay? And similarly, control records,
which is not even sent by broker, so
control records are also not visible.
So, in short,
you would be seeing only
non-transactional records, the records
which are not part of any transaction,
those would be visible, and only
committed one.
And only committed one.
So, in this example, what would be
visible?
Offset zero, offset one, part of
committed, so yes, you would be able to
see offset zero, you would be able to
see offset one.
But here, if you see offset two is open.
Okay? So, that won't be visible.
And after that,
you can't even if you see the offset
four is committed.
So, as per you, hey, Shreyansh, you said
that all the committed transaction
should be visible. So, offset four,
which is see, this is control record
committed. So, this should be visible
now. But, no.
That is not visible. So, only zero and
one would be visible.
Now, the question can come, why? Why not
offset four?
See, that's where LSO comes into the
picture.
I told you that broker
guarantee that when you are reading from
a particular partition, you would read
in order. Zero, one, two, three, four,
like this.
Okay?
Now, here,
and whatever we are saying that
the open transaction should not be
visible when we are following the read
committed isolation level.
So, how to skip? The first question is,
how
to
skip
open transaction?
So, that's where LSO help us. So, we
know that LSO points to the record,
first record, which is open.
Okay?
So, now,
when consumer is start reading,
so it will read offset zero. Yes. Okay?
It doesn't know whether it it is
committed.
Okay?
So, it will read it. I will tell you
forget about aborted one. Okay? First,
let's discuss
on open and commit. Open and commit.
Aborted one, let's keep it aside. I will
come again.
First, assume that we had only have uh
records which are either open or
committed.
So, now let's see.
Consumer is start reading it.
Okay? So, here, LSO is two.
So, first offset zero. Zero is less than
two? Yes, read it.
Then comes one.
One is less than two? Yes, read it. So,
zero is read, one is read.
Then comes offset two. Two is less than
LSO, LSO is two. So, two is less than
two, false. Uh stop.
Consumer will not read
from this point because this is open.
Not yet closed, not yet committed or
aborted, so this is open.
So, consumer will stop.
Now, you can say that why consumer
cannot skip and read this four? Because
I told you
that
broker guarantees that in a particular
partition, order is guaranteed. So,
it is possible that after a specific uh
sometime time out, this might get uh
committed, for example. This might get
committed.
So, zero, one, but if you skip at this
point of time,
and you read four, then you are breaking
this guarantee, ordering guarantee.
Okay? So, we should not break this
guarantee.
So, that's where LSO helps that, hey,
this is the first open transaction, you
should not read beyond this point.
Okay? Wait for it to get complete.
Okay? So,
when we have open and commit
transaction, that is properly handled.
So, it just simply read blindly.
Read all the offset less than LSO. So,
keep on reading, reading, reading, and
as soon as the LSO point comes, it will
stop, means there is an open
transaction. Don't read this and beyond.
Okay?
Now, you can say that, hey, if you are
saying that read blindly, there could be
possible that records
are part of aborted transaction.
Then how to skip it? For example, in
this case itself, what if this PID epoch
zero,
instead of this commit, there is abort?
Then how you will skip this?
That's the next thing.
How we will skip aborted record?
So, see this one very important part is
broker consumer.
When the consumer do poll,
broker only filtered, it only filter
control records.
Control records. It don't send control
records. Fine.
But, it do send records which are
aborted.
Uh with records
which are aborted.
So, if consumer read blindly
with this simple logic that LSO read
everything,
read every offset which is less than
LSO, then it is possible that it will
read the records which are part of
aborted transaction.
So,
alone LSO is not sufficient.
So, how consumer get to know what all
records I need to skip which are part of
aborted?
That's where broker comes into the
picture. Broker provide one more
information to consumer, a file.
You can say that it's a aborted file
transaction.
So, whenever any record which is or
transaction which is aborted,
broker is store
some information in the separate file.
And that file is given to the consumer.
I will show you with an example.
Understand this one.
Okay? So, now here, if you see
PID five epoch zero, this is part of one
transaction, PID five epoch zero,
and this is their commit. So, this is
committed.
Offset two, PID eight epoch one, this is
aborted.
This is
aborted. This is
committed.
Okay?
Similarly, PID nine epoch zero, this is
committed.
Okay? And PID eight
epoch one, transactional true. So, see,
now one very interesting point. I told
you that producer is single-threaded
transaction. Okay?
So, when one transaction is going on,
till it is not committed or aborted, you
can you cannot initiate another
transaction. Okay? So, that's where I
showed you that here, if you see
PID eight epoch one. So,
this is PID eight epoch one. So, this is
one transaction with PID eight
epoch one.
Okay?
This is one transaction going on. So,
first this transaction got committed or
aborted. So, this got aborted. So, means
this
got completed. So, this transaction got
completed.
So, now here, if you see again, PID
epoch one.
Another transaction. PID
epoch one, with same.
Because your producer can be same. And I
in the producer video, you got to know
that producer transaction video, you
know that it is just a
uh version of a producer.
So, it's possible that same producer
Okay, same version. It is starting
multiple transaction.
Okay, but only if you see that the first
PID and epoch one once we have a control
record, after that you have another
record with transaction true and then
recorded.
Okay, and here if you see it's control
record here.
Okay, it's control record committed.
Now, you have to consumer has to read
this.
Now, let's say consumer is following
read committed.
Means consumer has to read all the
commit transaction
all non-transactional records
and has to skip aborted
and open transaction.
So, that's the requirement.
So, what all things it will read?
So, first of all what broker will
return? Broker will return
offset zero
offset one
offset two
offset three it's a control, so it will
be skipped.
Offset four
offset five is control this will be
skipped. Offset six is control record
that would be skipped. Offset seven
offset eight is control and that would
be skipped.
So, this all would be returned by broker
to consumer. But here notice that
this producer ID epoch one offset two
one is aborted.
This need to be skipped.
But not this one. This producer ID epoch
one the same.
Offset two has producer ID epoch one.
Offset seven also has producer ID epoch
one same.
But this one is committed this one is
aborted.
So, while reading
consumer should only skip this offset
two.
How it will get to know that?
Okay.
So
this one I already told you that we only
need to skip offset two not offset seven
even though they attached the same
producer ID epoch one.
So, answer is broker itself. Broker
provide store maintain this file.
Abort file.
You can say that.
.txn index
whenever
any transaction is aborted it is stored
information like
hey, this is the PID eight epoch is one
first index is two and the control last
it's control index last is six.
So, here if you see
whenever this abort come
so, it has that hey, this is the
producer ID PID eight
epoch one
so, it's first record it's first record
comes at offset two
and the control record it's come at this
offset six.
So, it is stored this information and it
send this to consumer also.
Now, it send this to consumer also. So,
how consumer
use this?
So, consumer will say that okay, offset
zero
should I have to skip it or not?
Now, let's say that LSO is
there is no open transaction. So, LSO is
pointing to let's say till offset eight
now, so LSO is pointing to nine on
itself.
LSO equals to nine. Okay, let's say.
So, the consumer will read less than LSO
which is nine.
Okay, so offset zero less than LSO yes,
good. But do I still could be a part of
aborted? I need to check. So, it will
use this.
Hey
PID one in the aborted one
PID eight epoch one. This is PID five
different. Read it.
So, it will properly accept this and
read it.
Next offset PID five epoch one
offset one is less than nine yes, read
one filter
passed.
Second filter is is it aborted or not?
PID eight epoch one this is PID five
epoch zero different.
Read it properly.
Then offset two offset two is less than
LSO nine yes, one filter is passed.
Then I need to check whether it's a part
of aborted or not. PID eight epoch one
PID eight epoch one yes, same.
First offset two
and the last record control comes at
six. So, is it the offset between this
two?
It is offset two yes.
So, means it's a part of aborted
transaction so, skip it.
Similarly, offset four offset four less
than LSO nine yes
and PID nine epoch zero different. So,
read it.
Now, offset seven seven is less than LSO
yes, filter passed.
Now, whether it's an aborted? PID eight
epoch one yes
but the first offset is two
and the control it's come at six.
So, it's range is seven after this. So,
means it's a second transaction not the
one which was aborted. So, this would be
accepted.
So, this is how consumer handle
ongoing transaction with the help of LSO
commit generally it simply you can say
that do not handle it.
Only thing is it handle aborted.
Okay, through this file .txn index file.
Okay, so it
it skip ongoing open transaction it is
skip aborted ultimately read rest all.
Clear? So, this is how the transaction
index looks like whenever there is an
aborted
and this is the information it passed.
If you see that transaction index dump
producer ID
epoch version
first offset last offset. Last offset is
nothing but a
your control
a statement for this one.
Okay.
And LSO last stable offset it just
recorded. But also it
stored in in memory also.
So, let's see a demo.
But I hope this thing is clear.
Okay.
So, my servers controllers are running
brokers are all running.
Okay, so
let me start
producer is running.
So, consumer
So, first thing
in the consumer
application.properties
I have set read committed.
That's all.
Okay.
And now, let's see this one.
What happens? I just set this one.
And let me start the
consumer application.
So, consumer is up.
Okay, let me first
send the commit.
Okay, if you have already followed the
producer transaction you have already
seen this API first.
So
order three
I am hitting
so, it read consumer read it properly.
And also if we see
uh let me see in which partition it
goes.
It goes into
order goes into partition one.
Goes into partition one.
Partition one who is the owner of
partition one? Let me see.
>> [clears throat]
>> Just a sec.
So, we have three brokers, right?
So, partition order even partition one
and uh
let me check
first broker one is the leader.
Okay, so order three goes yeah.
So, it goes to the broker one itself. So
o-3 so, if you see
transaction true
producer ID zero epoch zero transaction
true this is the record.
And this is the control record for this
producer ID epoch commit.
And our consumer
able to read it properly.
Okay.
So, see this one.
Partition one leader was three
which is broker one.
Okay.
Now
I am testing the abort scenario.
Abort scenario
o-4
let's send it.
Aborted.
Does our consumer read it? No, o-4
doesn't come. It is skip it. But let's
validate our understanding.
So, we first need to see at which
partition it goes in the producer
it goes to the partition two offset two.
Partition two
leader is four which is your
uh broker two.
Okay, broker two is your
four because controller one is ID one
controller two is ID two controller
three is your broker one and controller
uh broker
four
is your
ID four.
Broker two is ID4. So, we need to check
the broker two logs.
So, here
let's see broker two.
Partition
two, right? So, it goes into partition
two. Okay.
Yes.
So, let me
hit it. So, here if you see
O-4.
So, this is first.
Is transactional true?
Okay. O-4.
And here if you see
the same producer ID epoch.
Is transactional true? Control true and
this is aborted.
So, don't worry about the this one
because see I'm making this video in
continuity of producer transaction. So,
that's why my application was on
controller and broker was all running.
And in the producer transaction, I have
also demoed the aborted scenario. Okay.
How aborted get appended to the logs.
So, this is from that one. Okay. So, I'm
making the video in continuation. So,
that's why these records are from the
previous part.
But this is O-4 is something which we
have just done now. So, this
when the producer has done
So, first it got a record here which is
is transactional and this is the
producer ID and epoch.
And
since it is aborted
then we have a control record and abort.
But here if you see our consumer haven't
read it O-4. How?
Now, if you see the broker two and
partition two, right? So, this is
order-event-2. So, this is the partition
two.
So, here if you see
it maintain \dot} txn index.
So, currently we are seeing the log
file.
So, this is our log file we are seeing.
Now, if we just see
txn
What was that?
txn index.
So, if you see this, what it maintains?
Producer ID, version, first offset two
last offset three. So, here if you see
offset two.
O-4. Last offset which is the control
one. So,
offset three is the one which is control
record abort.
So, that information is stored and this
file only help consumer to know which
transactions to
skip because they are aborted.
Got it?
Clear?
Very important LSO.
Which is used
to skip
open transaction.
And uh
the transaction index abort file. You
can say that abort file.
Which tell consumer that these all
records
belongs to a abort transaction. So, you
skip it.
Rest all trans Rest all records consumer
read it.
Now,
if you remember the producer transaction
while we discuss that what all problem
exist, I told that there is one problem.
Read, process, write problem which exist
at consumer side problem.
So, the problem is that
consumer first do the read.
Okay, let's say when it read the record
50 comes.
Okay. A record with offset 50. One
record with offset 50 comes.
It processes it.
Read, process and then it try to write
or publish
to another topic, let's say. It
publishing an event again.
And it does that. And after that it
trying to commit the offset, but that
got failed.
So, when the consumer try to do poll
again, it will again get this record
with offset 50 because it is not yet
committed. Offset is not yet committed.
So, it will get the same offset.
It will do the same processing and it
will publish the event again.
So, there is a process There is a
possibility that you publish the same
event again.
How to
You can say that how to
uh remove this problem?
See,
one thing is which transaction cannot
help is that if you are not publishing
to another event, only this. Then you
can say that also, hey
this is also duplicate. It is processing
the record duplicate.
But this is not what transaction can
help you with. What if you are
processing record is like sending email?
Sending email.
So, you you got this
record. You send an email.
And while committing the offset it got
failed.
While again reading you got the same
offset. You again send mail.
You can't
undo that one, right? Even though it's a
duplicate, it's an external system. You
can't undo that. So, transaction do not
help in this one.
What transaction help saying that, hey
if you have this scenario
when you read this
maybe whatever the processing after you
are writing to an another event.
Okay. So, if
commit is
offset commit is lost, then it is
possibility that you will write again.
So, that can be solved through
transaction.
Because now we are internal to Kafka.
Reading is internal.
Publishing to an event is internal and
committing
offset is internal. That if it is
internal to Kafka, that can be
controlled.
And this is what EOS. Very frequently
asked, what is EOS in Kafka? Exactly one
semantic problem. And this is exact EOS
problem. You can say that.
Read, process, write problem.
Okay. So, above problem happened because
write and commit offset is a separate
step. So, you first write into an event.
You are write an event and after you
trying to commit the offset.
Now, offset commit fail.
That's why you are reading it again.
You are processing it and you are
publishing to an another
again.
Because this is separate step. Step one,
step two.
So, what it does is in EOS
guarantee that there should not be any
duplicate in consumer when consumer is
doing reading the offset
and then publishing it to another event.
In that scenario
the EOS says that exactly one semantic,
no duplicate.
Okay. And how it will do? It will group
into one atomic
transaction.
Publish to
topic and offset commit tied together
into one transaction. If one fails
like
both will fail. You can say that.
So, in this use case
read, process, write and then commit
offset. EOS achieve through read
committed. So, your consumer should be
isolation level read committed.
Okay.
And since consumer also has to publish
also has to publish
an event, right?
So, idempotency
and transaction should be enabled.
So, EOS achieve through
See, I'm talking at consumer side. Don't
get mixed it with producer. So, consumer
is doing both. So, it is reading
and then publishing to an offset
publishing to a particular topic.
And then doing offset commit.
Okay. So, consumer is doing both.
Reading part and publishing also. So,
that's why EOS says that it can be only
achieved when consumer is following read
committed
plus since it is also performing
producer role, it should be idempotency
and transaction. Generally, if you are
doing transaction, idempotency is
already enabled. But it's still
specifically in the definition it's
mentioned like this.
Okay. And what does it does is it
combine into one atomicity of this part.
Write or commit offset.
Okay. If commit offset fail, this write
will also fail.
When this commit get properly done, then
only this write is properly singed up.
And how?
Very simple.
Okay. Everything we have seen.
So, now application.properties,
you know that consumer has lot of
properties added. Okay. So, one thing
isolation level we want is read
committed.
Auto commit is false. We don't want to
enable the auto commit. So, one thing we
have to just make it false.
And since we are also has to do the
producer level task of transaction, so
you just simply add transaction ID
prefix. Give some transaction ID.
And this two you don't have to do it
because
by default when transaction is enabled,
idempotency set to true and acknowledges
all. But just for
specific, I am adding it that
idempotency should be true and
acknowledgement should be all.
But
by default it will get enabled only when
you have added the transaction.
So, this is the property you have to
add.
Now
how the code changes would look like
for the read, write, read process,
write.
So
one thing
is that
very simple. So here if you see I have a
Kafka listener.
So you know that
in consumer
what happened is that for each record
this listener will get invoked.
Correct?
So means read is happened.
Now
I have started a transaction producer.
Now I'm doing producing part. Kafka
template. execute in transaction. In the
producer transaction part I have told
you that it internally it just begin the
transaction
then invoke this lambda
and then commit or abort if there is any
exception.
So read is already happened here.
Okay, any process you have to do, do it.
If you don't have to do it, don't do it.
Okay, so step two is optional process.
Okay?
So read is happened. Now is that we have
to write to particular topic.
So I'm writing.
Payment event key and result. Okay, this
is your object. This is key and this is
topic.
Okay? So now here if you see
what we are doing is we have to in the
one transaction we are trying to tie up
right and offset commit part.
So right I have added.
Now offset commit part.
So on offset commit part I am just
saying I am not committing here at this
point of time. I am just adding into the
buffer
that okay.
See offset.put.
Okay, for this record, for this topic,
this partition
this topic and whatever the partition
okay?
We have to increase the offset.
Plus one. So manually what I am doing is
I am just
increasing the counter of the offset for
this topic, this partition and just put
into a buffer.
So this is important. Send offset to
transaction.
It is not here sending.
It is not invoking broker.
Commit offset. No.
You can say that it just put into
buffer.
Okay? It just put into buffer that for
this topic, this partition, this is the
offset we have to commit.
Now
after
either commit or abort
that would be the point when it is
commit
ultimately it will also send offset
to the broker.
So here from this buffer it will read
and send the command to the broker.
That for this topic, this partition,
this is the offset need to need to
update.
Okay, but if there is an abort, it do
not even send it.
It do not even send it.
Okay? So that's what it So see EOS is no
just the you can say that
a term
exactly once semantic. Okay? But only
thing is
this is just one problem.
When consumer is reading the
record
plus writing the record.
So this problem can come
when there is an offset commit. Because
see one is said read it write it but it
offset commit failed.
Then it again during the next read it
will again read it, again write the same
thing.
So that is one problem and that problem
name is given EOS. How to solve this
problem through EOS.
Exactly once semantic.
So since it is reading it, the consumer
should follow
read commit it and since it's also
producing it, so it should also have a
proper transaction and item potency.
And a very simple part I have told you
that the main goal here is to group
together in one atomic operation
this right part
and this offset part.
So this are the two rights which are
happening, right?
So just club together into one
transaction.
Okay, so it read it properly. Okay? Now
in one transaction
the right part
and this This is the only part which we
have to see that send offset to
transaction.
Okay? This is used to just buffer.
That for this topic, this partition,
this is the
counter we have to This is the offset
we have to update. But it will not
update now.
It will be done into
commit.
And during abort case
when we have an abort case, exception
case, this will
command would not be sent to a broker to
update it.
Clear?
So this is very critical like very
frequently used LSO, last stable offset,
EOS. So this concept of the consumer. I
hope I think transaction should be super
clear now.
Okay? I tried to cover everything. But
if anything is missed or any doubt, let
me know in the comment section. Bye.